<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PAPER><mode2 name="b107078a" hasDoc="yes" version="1085" /><TITLE><s sid="1"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Absolute photolysis cross-sections for NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO, NaO2 and NaO3 : implications for sodium chemistry in the upper mesosphere</annotationART></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The compounds NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO and NaO2 are formed from meteor-ablated Na in the upper mesosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="3"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">This paper reports the absolute photolysis cross-sections of these species at selected wavelengths between 193 and 423 nm, measured by laser photofragment spectroscopy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="4"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sodium species were produced in both a slow flow reactor and a fast flow tube, by the addition of appropriate reagents to a flow of atomic Na from a heat-pipe oven.</annotationART></s> <s sid="5"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The pulsed photolysis source was either a Raman-shifted excimer laser or a Nd:YAG laser, and the resulting Na atoms were probed by laser induced fluorescence at 589.0 nm (Na(3 2P3/2–2S1/2)).</annotationART></s> <s sid="6"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements are reported at 200 and 300 K. A limited set of cross-sections for NaO3 was also obtained at 300 K. In the case of NaHCO3 , NaOH and NaO, the onset of photolysis is close to the thermodynamic threshold calculated from quantum theory.</annotationART></s> <s sid="7"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations using the CI-singles method predict excited states whose relative energies are in sensible accord with the bands in the experimental spectra, but which are too high in energy with respect to their respective ground states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="8"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photodissociation coefficients are then derived which are appropriate for modelling sodium chemistry in the upper mesosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="9"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis of the major sodium reservoir species, NaHCO3 , is shown to be an important route for recycling this compound, and is also predicted to produce the HCO3 radical, which should be stable under mesospheric conditions.</annotationART></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The layer of Na atoms that occurs globally between 80 and 105 km is formed by the ablation of sodium from the approximately 120 tons of interplanetary dust that enters the atmosphere each day<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1" /><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2" />.<XREF ID="fig1" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 1</XREF> is a schematic diagram of the chemistry that is believed to control the layer.<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="11"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ion–molecule chemistry is important above the peak of the layer at about 90 km, whereas below this altitude Na is oxidised to form a number of neutral species including NaO, NaO2 , NaOH and NaHCO3 .</annotationART></s> <s sid="12"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None">A recent laboratory study of the reaction between NaHCO3 and H has confirmed that the bicarbonate is the most stable reservoir for sodium immediately beneath the layer.<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="13"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent models of the Na layer, using rate coefficients that have all now been measured individually under conditions appropriate to the mesosphere, produce excellent agreement with the observed seasonal and latitudinal variations of the layer.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit3" /><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit5" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="14"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, these observations were almost exclusively of the night-time Na layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="15"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Recent advances in lidar technology permit fully diurnal measurements of the layer to be made on a routine basis, yielding both Na density and temperature (from the broadening of the hyperfine structure of the D2 line at 589.0 nm).<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit6" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="16"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to explain the complex diurnal variability of the Na density profile, several coupled factors need to be taken into account.</annotationART></s> <s sid="17"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, there is the effect of tidal dynamics on the layer.</annotationART></s> <s sid="18"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Indeed, the amplitudes and phases of the diurnal and semi-diurnal tides have been obtained from analysis of the Na temperature record.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit6" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="19"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, the odd oxygen and hydrogen chemistry, which controls the underside of the Na layer (<XREF ID="fig1" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 1</XREF>), exhibits a large diurnal variation below 82 km where the concentrations of O and H vary by orders of magnitude.</annotationART></s> <s sid="20"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, the sodium compounds themselves may photolyse significantly during daytime, contributing a further diurnal oscillation.</annotationART></s> <s sid="21"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is the subject of the present study.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="22"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None">In this paper we will describe measurements of the absolute photolysis cross-sections (to yield atomic Na) of the neutral Na-containing molecules in <XREF ID="fig1" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 1</XREF>, using a laser photofragmentation method.</annotationART></s> <s sid="23"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None">Ab initio quantum calculations will then be employed to interpret the results, before calculating photodissociation coefficients suitable for use in mesospheric models.</annotationART></s> <s sid="24"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None">These sodium compounds have very large dipole moments and therefore readily cluster with water, particularly at the low temperatures of the upper mesosphere during summer.<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit7" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="25"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None">The effect of this on the photolysis cross-sections will also be examined.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="26"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute photolysis cross-sections of NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO, NaO2 and NaO3 were determined by the technique of pulsed laser photolysis followed by laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) of the resulting Na atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="27"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None">This photofragmentation technique has been used previously by Silver et al<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit8" />. and Rajasekhar et al<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit9" />. to study the photolysis of NaCl and NaO2 , respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="28"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sodium compound NaX (where X = HCO3 , OH, O, O2 or O3) is produced in situ by essentially complete conversion of a flow of Na atoms entering the reactor from an oven, following the addition of appropriate reagents in large excess:<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" /><XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" /><XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" /><XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" /><XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />If the resulting flow of NaX is subjected to a laser pulse of fluence I0(λ) at wavelength λ, then in the limit of low light absorption the concentration of nascent Na atoms created by the pulse is given by<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />where σ(λ) is the absolute photolysis cross-section at λ to yield Na+X.</annotationART></s> <s sid="29"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that we assume here that the photolysis quantum yield following absorption of a photon is unity.</annotationART></s> <s sid="30"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None">This will be justified below.</annotationART></s> <s sid="31"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Na atoms will give rise to a measured LIF signal, Ifp , when the probe laser is triggered immediately afterwards.</annotationART></s> <s sid="32"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the absence of reagents, the LIF signal (If0) will be proportional to the total Na atom concentration.</annotationART></s> <s sid="33"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is equivalent to [NaX] when reagents are added, after making a small correction for differences in the rates of diffusion of Na and NaX (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="34"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since Ifp and If0 are measured with the same geometrical light collection factor and detection sensitivity, then<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />Thus, σ(λ) can be determined absolutely by measuring the ratio Ifp/If0 , and monitoring I0(λ).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="35"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None">Two experimental systems were used in this study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="36"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first, illustrated schematically in <XREF ID="fig2" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 2</XREF>, employed a stainless steel slow flow reactor that has been described in detail elsewhere.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit9" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="37"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The central chamber of this reactor is at the intersection of two sets of side-arms that cross orthogonally.</annotationART></s> <s sid="38"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">One set of arms provides the optical coupling of the lasers to the central chamber, as well as the means by which the flows of the reagents enter the chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="39"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A third side-arm was independently heated (520–555 K) to provide a source of Na atoms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="40"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A spiral of stainless steel mesh (gauge 150) was inserted into this heat pipe, along with solid Na spheres.</annotationART></s> <s sid="41"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Upon heating the mesh became wetted with molten Na, thereby greatly increasing the surface area exposed to the flow of N2 gas that entrained the Na vapour into the central chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="42"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This feature, together with accurate control of the heat pipe temperature (±1 K), ensured a stable flow of Na atoms during the experiments.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="43"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The central chamber is enclosed in an insulated compartment that can be filled with dry ice to cool it to about 200 K. The temperature of the gas flow in the chamber is monitored by a thermocouple permanently inserted about 1 cm below the path of the laser beams.</annotationART></s> <s sid="44"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Once in the chamber, the atomic Na was mixed with the reagent flows at a total pressure of about 3 Torr.</annotationART></s> <s sid="45"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The synthesis of NaHCO3 via reactions <XREF ID="eqn1 eqn2 eqn3" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">(R1)–(R3)</XREF> required some care.</annotationART></s> <s sid="46"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the one hand, sufficient CO2 had to be added to ensure that all the NaOH produced by (<XREF ID="eqn2" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">R2</XREF>) was converted to NaHCO3 ; on the other, competition for NaO from the reaction<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />had to be minimised.</annotationART></s> <s sid="47"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">A full kinetic model<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit4" /> was employed to optimise the reagent mixing ratios: at 300 K the reagents N2O/H2/CO2/N2 were typically added in the ratio 5 : 20 : 0.3 : 74.7 (at 200 K, [N2O] was increased because reaction (<XREF ID="eqn1" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">1</XREF>) has a significant activation energy<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit10" />).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="48"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis was carried out over a range of wavelengths from 193 to 423 nm, using a Raman-shifted excimer laser (Questek Model 2010, with unstable resonator optics) operating at 193 nm (ArF) or 248 nm (KrF).</annotationART></s> <s sid="49"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Raman shifter (Lambda Physik, model RS75) was filled with H2 (Air Products, 99.9999percent) or D2 (Messer, 99.7percent) to between 2.2 and 10 bar.</annotationART></s> <s sid="50"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The output beams were separated spatially using a Pellin–Broca prism.</annotationART></s> <s sid="51"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluences of the Raman-shifted beams were measured before and after the reactor using a Molectron J-25 Joulemeter (5 mm diameter circular element, calibrated to a recent factory reference) and a quartz beamsplitter.</annotationART></s> <s sid="52"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The fluence in the central chamber was then computed as the geometric mean of the two measurements.</annotationART></s> <s sid="53"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None">The Raman-shifted wavelengths and typical laser fluences in the reactor are listed in <XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="54"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The relative atomic Na concentration was measured by pumping one of the Na D-lines at 589.0 nm [Na(3 2P3/2–3 2S1/2)] using a N2-pumped dye laser, and observing non-resonant LIF at 589.6 nm through a narrowband interference filter (Janos Corp., FWHM = 0.2 nm).</annotationART></s> <s sid="55"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">A vertical side arm on the chamber provided the optical coupling to the photomultiplier tube (Thorn EMI Gencom, model 9816QB).</annotationART></s> <s sid="56"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The signal was captured by a gated integrator after pre-amplification (Stanford Research Systems, model SR445, 300 MHz).</annotationART></s> <s sid="57"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The linearity of the measured LIF signal with the Na atom density was regularly checked.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="58"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">During photolysis experiments, the dye laser triggered 8.7 µs after the photolysis pulse.</annotationART></s> <s sid="59"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None">During this period an insignificant fraction of the nascent Na atoms would have reacted with the oxidant (N2O or O2) in the chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="60"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None">When the Na concentration in the absence of reagents was being measured (i.e. If0), the total flow and pressure in the central chamber were maintained by increasing the N2 flow through the side-arms.</annotationART></s> <s sid="61"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to make a measurement of σ(λ), Ifp and If0 were obtained by averaging a minimum of 200 data points in each case.</annotationART></s> <s sid="62"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None">A background (zero) signal was also obtained by measuring the LIF signal with the reagents flowing through the reactor but the photolysis laser off.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="63"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A limited number of experiments were performed using a second experimental system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="64"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None">This was a fast flow tube, described recently by Cox et al.,<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit4" /> which operated at a pressure of 1.5 Torr with flow velocities of 12–24 m s−1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="65"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis cross-sections were determined using the same photolysis/LIF technique.</annotationART></s> <s sid="66"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None">Na vapour was produced in an oven at the upstream end of the tube, entrained in N2 and then mixed in the flow tube with reagents that were added sequentially to produce the same compounds as before.</annotationART></s> <s sid="67"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis cross-sections were determined using a frequency tripled or quadrupled Nd:YAG laser (Continuum Minilite).</annotationART></s> <s sid="68"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None">The beam energy was determined with a calibrated Molectron J-50 Joulemeter, and the beam area measured with photosensitive paper.</annotationART></s> <s sid="69"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None">This yielded fluences of 170 mJ cm−2 at 354.6 nm and 110 mJ cm−2 at 265.9 nm.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="70"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None">The cross-section measurements with both experimental systems were performed with a total Na concentration less than 1 × 109 molecule cm−3 in the photolysis region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="71"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is important in order to avoid the clustering of Na compounds to form dimers and higher polymers.</annotationART></s> <s sid="72"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None">Polymerisation should be a fast process because of the strong intermolecular forces resulting from the large dipole moments of these species (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="73"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absolute Na concentration was determined in a separate experiment where it was measured in the absence of reactants by the resonance absorption of the radiation from a Na hollow cathode lamp directed transversely to the flow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="74"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None">An absorption cross section of 1.85 × 10−11 cm2 for the [Na(3 2PJ–3 2S1/2)] transition was assumed.<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit11" /></annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="75"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None">N2 (BOC, 99.9999percent pure), N2O (Air Products, 99.99percent pure), CO2 (Air Products, 99.995percent pure), H2 (Air Products, 99.9999percent pure) and O2 (Air Products, 99.995percent pure) were used without further purification.</annotationART></s> <s sid="76"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Sodium metal spheres (3–8 mm, Aldrich Chem.</annotationART></s> <s sid="77"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None">Co., Inc.) were cleaned with solvent before insertion into the heat-pipe ovens.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photolysis cross-sections, σ(λ), were determined using <XREF ID="eqn7" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (II)</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="79"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None">Measurements of the NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO and NaO2 cross-sections were made at both 300 and 200 K, since the lower temperature is representative of the upper mesosphere.</annotationART></s> <s sid="80"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photolysis of NaO3 , which is a less important mesospheric species,<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit3" /> was only studied at 300 K. Diffusion corrections to σ(λ) were made in the following way.</annotationART></s> <s sid="81"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the slow flow reactor (<XREF ID="fig1" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 1</XREF>), the flow of Na atoms from the heat pipe into the central chamber is balanced by diffusion to the chamber walls of Na (in the absence of reagents) or of NaX.</annotationART></s> <s sid="82"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we have shown previously for this reactor,<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit12" /> the steady-state concentration of Na is given by FNa/kdiff(Na), where FNa is the flow rate of Na into the chamber from the heat pipe, and kdiff(Na) is the first-order loss of Na to the walls of the chamber, which closely approximates to a cylinder of radius r = 3 cm and length l = 6 cm. kdiff(Na) is given by<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />where D(Na) is the diffusion coefficient for Na in N2 , at the pressure and temperature of the central chamber.</annotationART></s> <s sid="83"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None">When reagents are added to the same flow of Na from the heat pipe, the steady-state concentration of NaX is by analogy FNa/kdiff(NaX).</annotationART></s> <s sid="84"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the cross-section σ(λ) needs to be corrected by the factor kdiff(Na)/kdiff(NaX) ≈ D(Na)/D(NaX).</annotationART></s> <s sid="85"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The diffusion coefficients used to make this correction are listed in <XREF ID="tab2" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 2</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="86"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None">When correcting the 200 K data, it was assumed that the diffusion coefficients of Na and NaX had the same temperature dependences.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="87"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">For the fast flow tube measurements, the diffusion correction was applied by assuming uptake coefficients for Na and NaX of close to unity on the walls so that strong radial concentration gradients would have developed in the tube.</annotationART></s> <s sid="88"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The first-order loss to the walls under laminar flow conditions was then described using the approximation of Huggins and Cahn.<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit13" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="89"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of NaOH and NaO2 , a movable injector was used to vary the point in the flow tube at which reagents were added to produce these species from Na.</annotationART></s> <s sid="90"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None">By observing the apparent change in σ(λ) as the injection distance was varied, the diffusional loss to the walls of NaOH and NaO2 was determined relative to that of Na.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="91"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting σ(λ) are listed in <XREF ID="tab3 tab4 tab5 tab6 tab7" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Tables 3–7</XREF> for the five sodium species that were studied.</annotationART></s> <s sid="92"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="None">The quoted 1σ errors are computed by combining in quadrature the statistical and systematic errors.</annotationART></s> <s sid="93"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None">The statistical error arises from the standard deviations in the measurement of If0 and Ifp (<XREF ID="eqn7" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (II)</XREF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="94"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">When using a strong photolysis laser line (e.g. the KrF primary) and if σ(λ) &gt; 10−18 cm2, this error was less than 10percent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="95"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, if σ(λ) was very small or the laser fluence was weak, then the statistical error could exceed 100percent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="96"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None">There are two significant sources of systematic error.</annotationART></s> <s sid="97"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">First is the uncertainty in the measured laser fluence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="98"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">This ranged from 4percent for the primary excimer lines to 20percent for the highly Raman-shifted beams.</annotationART></s> <s sid="99"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None">The YAG fluences were estimated to have an uncertainty of 13percent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="100"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The second systematic uncertainty is in the diffusion correction factor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="101"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For NaOH and NaO2 , the diffusion coefficients relative to D(Na) were measured using the fast flow tube (see above), and D(NaO) was determined in a previous flow tube study,<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit4" /> so the error in the diffusion correction factors for these species is better than 5percent.</annotationART></s> <s sid="102"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None">D(NaHCO3) and D(NaO3) were estimated from long-range capture theory,<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit14" /> using parameters calculated from quantum theory (see below); the uncertainty in their diffusion correction factors is estimated to be 12percent.</annotationART></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Ab initio quantum calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="103"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The experimental measurements were complemented by a series of ab initio quantum calculations using the Gaussian 98 suite of programs.<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit15" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="104"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground-state geometries of NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO and NaO2 and NaO3 were first optimised using Hartree–Fock (HF) theory with the large flexible 6-311+G(2d,p) basis set, which has both polarization and diffuse functions added to the atoms.<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit16" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="105"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None">These molecules all have highly ionic ground states with large dipole moments (6.9, 6.6, 8.6, 8.3 and 7.4 D, respectively).</annotationART></s> <s sid="106"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have published the details of their geometries and vibrational frequencies elsewhere.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit4" /><REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit17" /><REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit18" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="107"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Calculations on the vertical electronic excited state energies and transition oscillator strengths were performed using configuration interaction-singles (CIS) theory.<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit15" /><REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit16" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="108"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to investigate the photolysis products of NaHCO3 , calculations were performed on the HCO3 radical using hybrid density functional/Hartree–Fock B3LYP theory with the 6-311+G(2d,p) basis set.</annotationART></s> <s sid="109"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"><XREF ID="fig3" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 3</XREF> illustrates the optimised geometry of this species, as well as the saddle-point geometry for dissociation to OH+CO2 .</annotationART></s> <s sid="110"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None">Finally, calculations were carried out on the ground and excited states of the NaOH–H2O and NaHCO3–H2O complexes, to examine the effect of water clustering on photolysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="111"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None">The H2O binding energies were determined using the very accurate complete basis set (CBS-Q) theory,<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit19" /> and the calculations on the excited states of the clusters were determined at the CIS/6-311+g(2d,p) level.</annotationART></s> <s sid="112"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None">The ground state geometries of these clusters are also illustrated in <XREF ID="fig3" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 3</XREF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="113"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Inspection of <XREF ID="tab3 tab4 tab5 tab6" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Tables 3–6</XREF> shows that the cross-sections measured in the flow reactor and the fast flow tube agree very well, even though the Na compounds were prepared somewhat differently in each type of system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="114"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"><XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF> illustrates the photolysis cross-section spectra of NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO2 and NaO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="115"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None">Note that the maximum cross-section for NaHCO3 is a factor of 10 smaller than the maxima in the spectra of the other compounds, and it only begins to absorb quite far into the ultra-violet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="116"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None">Shown on the figure and also listed in <XREF ID="tab2" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 2</XREF> are the thermodynamic limits to photolysis, calculated from the respective bond energies D0(Na–X).</annotationART></s> <s sid="117"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The sources of these bond energies are given in the footnotes to <XREF ID="tab2" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 2</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="118"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp5" novelty="None" advantage="None">For NaHCO3 , NaOH and NaO, the thermodynamic limit is close to the onset of photolysis in each case, implying that the relevant excited states have rather flat potential energy curves i.e. they are essentially covalent and at best weakly bound.</annotationART></s> <s sid="119"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is supported by the CIS quantum calculations, which show that the Mulliken electron population on the Na atom, which is greater than +0.9 in the ground state, is less than +0.1 in these excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="120"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None">These calculations indicate that transitions to these covalent states should lead to prompt dissociation to Na atoms.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="121"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None">The CIS method, which models excited states as combinations of single substitutions out of the Hartree–Fock ground state, is an approximate treatment for excited states.<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit16" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="122"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the present case it systematically over-predicts the vertical excitation energies from the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="123"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">In order to obtain sensible agreement with the positions of the observed absorption bands, the upper states of each molecule were shifted downwards by the same amount with respect to the ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="124"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None">These shifts are listed in <XREF ID="tab8" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 8</XREF> for the five molecules, and range from 0.6 to 2.7 eV.</annotationART></s> <s sid="125"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The (shifted) wavelength positions for transitions where the transition oscillator strength f is greater than 10−3 (and therefore significant), are marked on the top abscissa of each of the panels in <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF> along with their f values.</annotationART></s> <s sid="126"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is reasonable agreement with the measurements, implying that the relative energies of the covalent upper states are quite well predicted with respect to each other.</annotationART></s> <s sid="127"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, the change from ionic to covalent character between the ground and the upper states is not well described by CIS theory, since the Hartree–Fock orbitals used to describe the excited states are biased to the ground-state configuration.<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit16" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="128"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"><XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF> shows that some of the bands of NaO and NaO2 exhibit marked positive temperature dependences.</annotationART></s> <s sid="129"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None">A smaller dependence may be present in the case of NaOH, whereas NaHCO3 exhibits no apparent dependence.</annotationART></s> <s sid="130"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp6" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is probably explained by vibrational excitation of the ground state molecule leading to better Franck–Condon overlap with its excited states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="131"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None">For example, CIS calculations show that the ground state of NaOH is linear, whereas the covalent excited states are bent: hence, excitation in the degenerate bending modes should increase σ(λ).</annotationART></s> <s sid="132"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"><XREF ID="tab2" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 2</XREF> lists the lowest vibrational frequencies of NaHCO3 , NaOH, NaO2 and NaO, and the ratios of the Boltzmann population of v′′ = 1 at 300 K compared to 200 K. This ratio increases markedly from 1.3 for NaHCO3 to 3.3 for NaO, in accord with the observed variation in temperature dependence shown in <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="133"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is an interesting aspect to the spectrum of NaO in the near ultra-violet.</annotationART></s> <s sid="134"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Langhoff et al<REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit20" />. carried out multi-reference configuration-interaction calculations on the first three states of NaO.</annotationART></s> <s sid="135"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">This showed that the C 2Π state should be accessible about 25 000 cm−1 (≈400 nm) above the X 2Π ground state.</annotationART></s> <s sid="136"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None">Furthermore, because the equilibrium Na–O separation of the C state is about 1.5 Å larger than the X state, the theory predicted that NaO(C–X) absorption would be followed by emission to high vibrational levels of the X state, producing a band system from 500 to 2000 nm and peaking around 1000 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="137"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">However, Pugh et al<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit21" />. failed to observe an LIF spectrum for NaO in the 390–430 nm region.</annotationART></s> <s sid="138"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Ellis has reported a similar finding.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="139"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None">The absence of fluorescence is now explained by the present study, which shows that absorption in this region leads to photolysis (<XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="140"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None">The implication is that NaO(C 2Π) is crossed by a higher-lying 2Π state, causing pre-dissociation to Na+O.</annotationART></s> <s sid="141"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None">Further theoretical work should be carried out on this system.</annotationART></s> <s sid="142"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None">It should also be noted that the reaction between Na and N2O produces NaO in both the X(2Π) and A(2Σ+) states.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit23" /><REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit24" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="143"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is some evidence that NaO(A 2Σ+) is not quenched very efficiently, and has a radiative lifetime of more than 20 ms.<REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit24" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="144"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">Hence, the cross-sections measured in this study may describe a mixture of the X and A states.</annotationART></s> <s sid="145"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp7" novelty="None" advantage="None">These are separated by about 2050 cm+1,<REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit20" /><REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit24" /> corresponding to ≈20 nm in the near-UV, which may explain the rather broad bands in the NaO spectrum (<XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>).</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="146"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The results for NaO2 are in excellent agreement with a previous study using a slow flow reactor.<REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit9" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="147"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The only other work on the absorption spectrum of NaO2 appears to be a matrix isolation study where Na atoms and O2 were co-deposited in argon.<REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit25" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="148"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None">The resulting superoxide species gave rise to bands with maxima at 232, 250 and 272 nm, which correspond approximately with bands in the 200 K spectrum in <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="149"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None">An absolute absorption spectrum for NaOH in the ultraviolet has been obtained by Rowland and Makide,<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit26" /> based on spectroscopic data when aqueous NaOH solutions were aspirated into flames between 900 and 2300 °C.</annotationART></s> <s sid="150"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"><XREF ID="fig5" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 5</XREF> is a comparison of the flame absorption cross-section spectrum with the photolysis spectrum from the present study.</annotationART></s> <s sid="151"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None">There is generally good agreement in the absolute magnitudes of the cross-sections, particularly for the strong band around 235 nm and in the absence of absorption between 265 and 290 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="152"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">The discrepancy beyond 310 nm could be caused by hot-band absorption by vibrationally-excited NaOH in the high temperature flames: indeed, Rowland and Makide<REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit26" /> pointed out that the flame absorption spectrum continued beyond the thermodynamic limit set by the D0(Na–OH) bond energy (see below).</annotationART></s> <s sid="153"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp8" novelty="None" advantage="None">Another possibility is that the apparent structure in the flame spectrum beyond 320 nm is actually due to other absorbing species present in the flame that were not accounted for in the analysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="154"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None">Finally, it should be noted that photolysis at 193 nm of NaOH produces Na(3 2P) which then fluoresces at 589 nm.</annotationART></s> <s sid="155"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is employed as a diagnostic for sodium in combustion systems, where NaOH is the dominant form at temperatures above 1500 °C.<REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit27" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="156"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None">The threshold for Na(2P) production is about 226 nm, which is close to the onset of the third absorption band in the NaOH spectrum in <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>.</annotationART></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Atmospheric implications</HEADER><P><s sid="157"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None">The photodissociation coefficients for these Na-containing species were computed from the relation:<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />where Φ(λ) is the solar actinic flux in the upper mesosphere.<REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit28" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="158"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None">The integration was performed by using a smooth interpolation between the experimental results at discrete wavelengths (see <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="159"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of NaO2 , where photolysis at wavelengths longer than 440 nm is thermodynamically possible, the CIS calculations indicate that there are no low-lying states (<XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4</XREF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="160"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None">Photolysis at wavelengths shorter than 190 nm will make only a minor contribution to J because the solar flux decreases very rapidly in the vacuum ultra-violet.<REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit28" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="161"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">The calculated J values and the lifetimes of the molecules against photolysis are listed in <XREF ID="tab9" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 9</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="162"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None">In a previous study of the photolysis of NaO2 where σ(λ) was only measured at three wavelengths,<REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit9" /> the estimate of J(NaO2) = (4.8 ± 2.8) s−1 is about a factor of 2 larger than the result of the present study, although there is agreement within the quoted error.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="163"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"><XREF ID="fig6" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 6</XREF> compares the calculated J values for the four important Na species with their most rapid chemical loss processes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="164"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None">These involve reaction of atomic H with NaHCO3 and NaOH, atomic O reacting with NaO and NaO2 .</annotationART></s> <s sid="165"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None">The conditions are midday in June at 40 °N (see the figure caption for further details).</annotationART></s> <s sid="166"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of NaO and NaO2 , photolysis is not competitive: atomic O is very abundant in the upper mesosphere, and these species react rapidly with O.<REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit14" /><REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit29" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="167"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, photolysis of NaHCO3 and NaOH dominates their removal during daytime: atomic H is 2–3 orders of magnitude less abundant than O, and the rates of the reactions of these species with H are quite slow.<REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit3" /><REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit4" /></annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="168"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None">In terms of understanding the chemistry of Na in the mesosphere, the photolysis of NaHCO3 is clearly important since this species is believed to be the major gas-phase sodium reservoir below about 85 km.<REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit3" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="169"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None">With a lifetime against photolysis of only about 2 h, a large diurnal cycle in atomic Na below 85 km would be predicted.</annotationART></s> <s sid="170"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None">Since this is not in fact observed,<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit6" /> NaHCO3 must be removed from the system, most likely through uptake on meteoric smoke particles.<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit30" /></annotationART></s> <s sid="171"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None">We are currently examining this with a new diurnal Na model.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="172"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp9" novelty="None" advantage="None">NaHCO3 and NaOH have very large dipole moments (see above), so that they can form stable H2O clusters and this may affect their rates of photolysis.</annotationART></s> <s sid="173"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None">CBS-Q calculations indicate that the binding energies of H2O to NaHCO3 and NaOH are 51.7 and 84.5 kJ mol−1, respectively.</annotationART></s> <s sid="174"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None">As we have shown previously,<REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit7" /> even in the very dry mesosphere with H2O mixing ratios of a few ppm, these (and higher) clusters will dominate once the temperature falls below about 170 K. This situation occurs during mid-summer, particularly at high latitudes.</annotationART></s> <s sid="175"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">CIS calculations on the excited states of NaHCO3·H2O show that the vertical excitation energies of the first 5 excited states increase by 31–62 kJ mol−1; for NaOH·H2O, the increase is 65–113 kJ mol−1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="176"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">These energy ranges are consistent with the respective binding energies of the clusters.</annotationART></s> <s sid="177"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None">This is to be expected, because H2O binds strongly to the ionic ground states of these molecules (<XREF ID="fig3" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 3</XREF>), but is weakly bound to the covalent upper states.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="178"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None">To test the effect of cluster formation, we performed a simple experiment on NaOH photolysis in the slow flow reactor.</annotationART></s> <s sid="179"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None">A flow of H2O was added to the central chamber at 200 K, where the equilibrium H2O concentration of 5.3 × 1013 cm−3 was sufficient to convert the NaOH overwhelmingly to the H2O cluster.</annotationART></s> <s sid="180"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">The large peak in the photolysis cross-section spectrum of NaOH, σ(231.2 nm) = (18.2 ± 0.18) × 10−18 cm2, was reduced to (−0.13 ± 0.15) × 10−18 cm2, i.e. effectively zero.</annotationART></s> <s sid="181"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None">In contrast, σ(248.4 nm) changed from (1.73 ± 0.13) × 10−18 cm2 to (0.361 ± 0.044) × 10−18 cm−2.</annotationART></s> <s sid="182"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp10" novelty="None" advantage="None">These changes would be accounted for if the NaOH spectrum was shifted to shorter wavelengths by the equivalent of 75 kJ mol−1, which is consistent with the NaOH–H2O binding energy.</annotationART></s> <s sid="183"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None">If the NaHCO3 photolysis spectrum is also shifted to shorter wavelengths by the NaHCO3–H2O binding energy, as predicted by theory, then the lifetime against photolysis in the mesosphere would increase from 2.2 to 4.5 h.</annotationART></s></P><P><s sid="184"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None">In the case of NaHCO3 , the CIS excited state calculations show that the vertical transitions with large oscillator strengths (f &gt; 0.02) that contribute to the absorption band between 210 and 230 nm all lead to dissociation to Na and the HCO3 radical (<XREF ID="fig3" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 3</XREF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="185"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None">It has been speculated that HCO3 could be formed in the atmosphere from the reaction<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS" />However, the present calculations reveal two significant features on the potential energy surface of reaction (<XREF ID="eqn11" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">R7</XREF>).</annotationART></s> <s sid="186"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">First, the complex is weakly bound, ΔH0°(7) = −14 ± 20 kJ mol−1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="187"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Second, there is a significant barrier ΔE0# = 74 kJ mol−1 for HCO3 to dissociate to OH+CO2 .</annotationART></s> <s sid="188"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None">Thus, reaction (<XREF ID="eqn11" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">R7</XREF>) is likely to be extremely slow.</annotationART></s> <s sid="189"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">On the other hand, HCO3 will also not dissociate very rapidly.</annotationART></s> <s sid="190"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod15" novelty="None" advantage="None">We have estimated the rate of thermal dissociation using Rice–Ramsberger–Kassel–Marcus (RRKM) theory<REF ID="R-54" REFID="cit31" /> with the data in <XREF ID="tab10" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 10</XREF>.</annotationART></s> <s sid="191"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None">This indicates that at a pressure of 0.01 Torr (the pressure at 80 km in the atmosphere), the rate of dissociation of HCO3 is 1.4 × 108 exp(−8400/T) s−1.</annotationART></s> <s sid="192"><annotationART atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None">Even allowing for the expected uncertainty<REF ID="R-55" REFID="cit16" /> of ±14 kJ mol−1 in the calculated barrier height, HCO3 should be thermally stable for at least several days at 80 km, and is likely to be destroyed much more rapidly by reaction with atomic O or H.</annotationART></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>
